Sophie Friedman Papers, 1795, 1906-1954
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Sophie Friedman papers
1795, 1906-1954
Friedman, Sophie, 1878-
MS 58
1 box (.25 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Lawyer. Papers document Friedman's work as a lawyer in Tennessee and for women's suffrage, uniform marriage, divorce laws, child welfare, adult education, social hygiene and international friendship. Included is material relating to her defense of Octavia Dockery and Richard Dana in the famous "Goat Castle case" in Natchez, Mississippi (1930s).
Sophie Friedman was born in Austria-Hungary in 1878. She graduated Memphis (Tennessee) University of Law, 1922 and became the first woman to practice law in Natchez, Mississippi. She was a member of the Tennessee State Supreme Court, the Federal District Court, and the Circuit Court of Appeals. She was also a state officer of the National Association of Women Lawyers and served as delegate to the State Democratic Convention in 1936. Friedman was a member of the Women's Congress at Memphis, the League of Nations Association for Tennessee, the League of Women Voters, and many other women's legal and civic organizations. She was also involved in international relations, peace, and the welfare of women and children. She sponsored several bills for social legislation in the General Assembly of Tennessee and was active in ratification of Tennessee for Universal Women's Suffrage.
The Sophie Friedman Papers include correspondence, drafts of legislative bills, photographs, clippings, articles and reports documenting Friedman's work as a lawyer in Tennessee and her work for women's suffrage in the state; her crusade for uniform marriage and divorce laws; and for child welfare, adult education, social hygiene and international friendship. Included is material relating to her defense of Octavia Dockery and Richard Dana in the famous "Goat Castle case" in Natchez, Mississippi (1930s).
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
This collection has not been fully processed.
Search Terms
Friedman, Sophie, 1878-; Lawyers--Tennessee--Biography--Sources; League of Nations--History--Sources; League of Women Voters (U.S.)--History--Sources; Women lawyers--United States--Biography--Sources; Women--Suffrage - Tennessee--History--Sources; Law--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Marriage law--United States--History--20th century--Sources
Container List
- Biography, 1932-52, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Clippings, 1938-53 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence
  - Incoming, 1930-53, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Outgoing, 1931-53 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- American Bar Association, 1930-51, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- League of Nations, 1928-42, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- League of Women Voters, 1920-53, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Marriage Law, 1927-47, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Merrill Murder Case (Goat Castle Case), 1932-48, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Miscellaneous, 1925-38, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Natchez Trace, 1795-1949, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Suffrage, 1906-54, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)